Oh, that says six on that.
Now we'll call it over the Braggler Skitter Me in my city council
for Monday, November 6th, 2023.
But the input on Skitter Personal Pairances.
Good morning.
We had none.
Three claims list.
Thank you.
Hi.
Williams.
Right.
Done, go ahead.
He's done.
All right.
Four minutes from the October 16th,
and October 23rd, Braggler Skitter Me.
Motion to complete.
Thank you.
Parker.
Williams.
Done, go ahead.
These steps.
Thank you.
5, budget amendment number 24, 10, 06, fire,
receding and expanding the $5,000 donation for tools,
and receding and spending a $26,000, $36, not not
since AFG grant.
You purchase eight sets of booker here.
This is for you.
Oh, I'll make a motion to do it.
Thank you.
Parker.
I'm sorry, Williams.
Hi.
Thank you.
These steps.
Six, ordinance 20, 23, does 08 for vacation of seven.
Vacation of seven feet right, street right away.
Locate that 21, 10, east, steep ones, both are dollar general.
My, I'm a 24, 4, 4, 3, L, L, C.
Has recommended by the city zoning and planning commission.
Yes.
So, dollar general on, Steve Owens, 21, 10, east,
Steve Owens.
I have my panel here.
So, basically, what's happened is, at some point,
a seven foot wide right away was platted.
Poor house in 1988, there's no use for that right away.
We looked at your packets by included a Google Earth
in-inch, kind of highlighted the right away coming off
of Steve Owens.
We think possibly, we got surveyed wrong.
It should have been here when they developed.
It has to be a part of it.
I said, repellent the Earth's tube.
Do you think that is that they have the land behind it?
They do have some utilities that run north or south to their property from our utility lines that run east west behind
Revealment is a lot, but I think they're working out of the easement, but it's private so reason to have a right way
It was getting ready to say out. We had this meeting last week. There's last Thursday. Last Thursday. I said in on that
It's pretty pretty straightforward. Just correcting mistake. It was made a long time ago
I'm going to rush to approve. Parker. Hi. Williams.
Hi.
Thank you.
Thank you, guys.
Seven, renewal, annual contract, C-21, Dastrict Board, Monday, Mayfield Davis.
For as needed, there are services for fiscal year 23, 24, most of them.
Thank you.
Parker. Hi. Williams.
Thank you. Hi.
This step.
Hi.
Hey, purchase a place or a enterprise subscription, which will provide consumer data for the city of Miami.
Okay. You guys have the information in your packet. I know we've worked on this for a long time.
This is going to be a new program that we're going to be able to utilize. All departments will be able to utilize this.
You can see the information there in your background. It will provide unique data, services support and features.
It will give us the opportunity to really study consumer habits and behaviors in the way that visitors and locals.
The way that they do things for their entail. I also gave you guys a couple of examples there that you can look at some more of the information.
One of the examples that gave you, the two guys have in there, is that it shows you a visitor's journey from doing a geophants around McDonald's.
It actually shows you guys when they leave from home, they go there. When they leave there, the different places that they go.
Really overall, just assist us in really trying to evaluate helps with visitor development.
It's going to help with economic development. I said it will be a tool that all departments will have access to.
One of the things that we targeted with this and why we're specifically using some of our funds that we've set aside for
the relicensing for the floods is being able to learn what happens during high water events.
We'll be able to determine not only look at past data
at how it affected the economy, businesses, schools,
just the general flow of traffic and the impact of business.
During the flood, we'll be able to recognize natural trends
without my water events.
And then as new water, I were events in my curve.
We could then begin studying the impact that had on our economy.
So it could be a very key tool in understanding
how and what roads are affected in businesses.
So we're really excited for this tool.
And then the neat thing is, is everybody that has a
MIMA city email address will have to count.
So all of the council will have access,
all of our police department department,
and so they'll be able to gain access to this data
to understand trends and patterns.
How does that work?
So all of us carry around these devices.
These devices are constantly tracking where you're going,
where you came from, where you stopped.
If you set somewhere longer than I think seven minutes,
it considers that a visit to visit that location.
And then you went on to somewhere else.
Now, none of that data that this company or any of these companies
store and produce these reports is specific about a person.
It's really just a general number of zip code,
or area you came from, and where you went.
So it just gives us information that I agree with.
So you can ask for a problem number and get it.
No phone numbers, no specific information like that.
But it can tell you that, 10 people from backster,
drove to town, Friday, 9, and 8, it's on.
When they left on, you've been going to pull up.
Two hours now.
Anytime we have minutes.
19 minutes.
We know how quick.
When they come to a cold with a bit, we know how far they travel.
And then they have a price on area.
I'm sorry.
And then they have a price.
It's 17,000.
It's an annual subscription.
Yeah.
17,000 a year.
Yep.
What will it cost to do about 200 accounts per year?
One of the examples bone I've been on numerous demos with this company.
One of the things that has slowed it down a little bit is that this company
is used to being able to sell source.
And because working with Brian, we had a lot of hoops to go through because it really actually
is not a product that can be sold sourced.
So we had to really go out and try to get bits.
It's secure comparisons for this exact type of data.
We were able to go out and find a comparison.
And I mean, that product was $25,000 a year.
So it did some things differently.
But everything that we're looking for in this kind of what our need is.
I don't like this company.
It's satisfied on that.
It's a good question.
I mean, I've still got to be able to get a PO through the system, so do you guys approve it tonight?
We'll interact tomorrow, so then it's going to still be another two week process
before it can hit a council meeting then, I guess, for, because it's an annual contract,
so to go through the tracking system.
I would love to say within, by four weeks, but a lot of it's just going to depend internally on how
could that PO can get pushed through, and then you guys will approve it at the next, at your next meeting
for purchase.
Where's the money coming from?
It's coming out of our budget for our 7,000 or 50,000 that we've budget for a lot, before we
rely since, so I can try to put it in.
So I don't know if you've heard that, Kevin, but it'll allow us to be able to track and the impact
to the economic development of businesses during high water events, so I could tell you that,
you know, this meeting number of people coming into business on our main street in a normal week,
but during a high water event when the roads were blocked, nobody got through it,
it'll show us that data of what the impact was, could the kids get to school, could people get
to work, could people get the stores to shop, to eat, how do you monetize that information?
How do you know what it does?
So they've got it all built into their algorithms, it's, it's really slick.
So when it's some of the demos, just so you guys will know, we did a demo on two different
convenience stores, one on Steve Owens and one on Main Street, during the last big flood event,
and we were able to see that data and that kind of the consumer behavior from that person,
prior to the flood, and you remember that water was high on Steve Owens for a very, very long time.
So we were able, Bo and I, from that demo, we could go in and see where the attendees and the
number of people going into those stores, I mean, it just scary fell off, it's like it closed overnight
and then you can go a couple weeks later and you see the dots where they're starting to come back in
from, but you can even, I mean, you can take that data and it'll tell you where they're coming in,
we did a comparison on Joplin, 7 Street, Walmart versus Miami Walmart and the amount of people in
Southeast Kansas and Southwest Missouri that was actually coming in to shop at the Miami Walmart was,
I mean, it shows you the dots for all those people travel in from. So another demo we did was after the
second heritage fest, we went in and built a geofints around the entire heritage fest area and we asked
it to give us the data for, we're venue 29 was where the concerts were held versus another music venue
that was in Pittsburgh Kansas that had a big country singer there that night as well and it showed us
the data from where people traveled before they went to those two locations. I think ours, we had nine
different states that it immediately identified that was at ours and there were two states at the other one
where people drove in from different places. So that was my first kind of looking at it.
It really just gives us the ability for as we sell and market the city. It's going to give us
something to put in our hands. We have a lot of revenue we bring in from outside to supplement the tourism budget.
And when we're soliciting fundraising and sponsorships and we're not asking people for donations
It's just another tool for the not just tourism but really other departments as well to have to show
That we're actually going to have some data and research that shows where people are coming in from and then what their shopping habits or behaviors are when they're here
Well, everything that our guys have to do in our system, where's it all on their system?
Jeff and Keith sit in on a demo with me as well. So it's all in the cloud
It's contained outside of our system
So what's the chances of getting this up and running by November 17?
It depends on how I mean as long as we can get it for all the approvals and get a PO. I mean I can have it in on my end tomorrow
But at least control after that
If it's still available even if we don't get it activated by then the data
What is it? Yeah, we can go back to around around
Okay, well, I work because we'll go back and track this holiday season then absolutely absolutely
We did a we did a geofancer round
The Coleman like it'll tell us well the festival some people left the festival that first year the top three places
They went to Walmart and then they went to Sonic and then they went to Buffalo, Rancasino
So it showed us everybody that was in that geofans when they left that area
They're very next place. They went those were the three top locations
They visited when they left that concert
Did you get that information from the company from place or for this company?
We don't know who the people are we just know they're
We just know how what their chocolate behavior was
Especially for what we're going to use it for
The real licensing and the impact of the high water bits
And you know what we try it. We all utilize it if in a year that we come back together and say we just don't feel like it
I mean, I that this is why it's an annual and get any time we can go back and not renew our pride
I have a feeling we're going to find a lot of uses for it
I think
He's going to find uses for it. I think I was going to find uses for it
And I think just about all of our departments are going to find a lot of search warms wouldn't
Sorry, I
The type we can do is to sit it on that though, right? I mean that the search we'd be able to do I mean you can if you think about it
You can geofans a particular business
Geofans a business that say
And it'll tell you where everybody's coming from that, just make sure they're at rest.
That's what they're going to start talking about.
If we leave half of these people coming across state lines, it's going to show that.
It's going to show that.
So to take it, does it take you right back to your residence?
It'll show you, if you look in your packet.
So what does this particular report shows you, like, it's a geo fence around McDonald's.
And it shows you this particular time frame.
That 49.5% of people that were going to McDonald's when they left McDonald's.
They either went straight to 7.9% went to work.
4.5% left McDonald's and went to Walmart.
3.5% left McDonald's and went to any O&M college.
The mayor will like this.
0.8% left and went to Taco Bell.
They left McDonald's and went to Taco Bell.
That was me.
Yeah.
But there's my grandkids.
There's another statistic for you.
In this particular event, this was from September 21st through August of 22.
When people left Buffalo, around Casino, 1.2% of people when they left there.
61% of them went straight home.
They went to McDonald's and then from McDonald's they went straight home.
So they left the Casino went to McDonald's and ate.
And then they went home.
They went home.
So it's a lot of it's kind of spooky when you look at it.
But like here's another report for you guys.
It's the same thing.
It's Sonic.
I mean, 45 or 45.7% of people left home went to Sonic.
And then 0.6% of them went to the gym.
After the film.
Wow.
So I mean, it's homework, Walmart, any of you.
It just.
Yeah.
And then if you look in your packet, there's another one here.
It ranks us versus Walmart.
Seven straight in Walmart.
So it's going to tell us how many people are staying in
Joplin versus what range of people are leaving that region and
coming and shopping in Miami.
It'll like it tells us what our Sonic and our McDonald's ranks.
It compared to other ones.
We sell something.
I have a machine to Larry.
Yeah.
I see Larry already knows.
I'm pretty sure.
There will help.
Miami figure out what Miami is losing sales tax to in in surrounding communities.
Like Joplin.
Yeah.
Water people in Miami going to drop in the shop for a where are they going to shop?
And could we have that shop here?
And I think that'll help tell us that we'll help us go recruit.
That's a great point.
And then also, so Kishen, I are working with the department of commerce right now on some
leakage reports.
So we're going to have that data for you guys here pretty quick too.
That's going to show you where we're losing business at.
Like if they're not, if we don't have them downtown shopping, where are they shopping at?
I'll tell you this thing.
That this weekend, you know, I get a phone call from local in California.
Answer it.
And it's an investor.
I want the talk.
about my ammo. So I get bow on the bone. Just got to ask us 50 J in questions. This
the operation would have been brilliant because he was asking all these questions. Of course,
we talked about what we could tell him. And then I used to go and make a trip here and come and check
us out. So this information could be really valuable. And those calls come in.
And this as you guys, we just brought on a new position in the CVB. It's an office assistant kind of
administrative role, Jesse, that's worked for us forever. And this is something that kind of
he'll lead up just as far as being that person that's pulling information for us and going back
and tracking a lot of steps. So we'll all do it. But hopefully there's questions or things like that
that you that pop up that you need help with that we want to get him trained up so he can be a resource to.
It's spooky. I'm not going to lie. It's, um, yeah. True. All my emotions, too, please.
Second. Perfect. Hi. Williams? Hi. Beckl. E steps. Hi. Thank you.
Nine. The award-lars will be in the least purchase agreement. The first national bank for Q23-54.
Great. 2020-34. Explore and get related to signing. Payment authority to City Manager is a
designate. We, uh, we've met the seven, uh, next this time. First national bank, uh, the lowest interest rate.
So first national banks became, uh, came in at 1,096 less than. Who are these four?
These are, for the police department, for police officials. All three. Yeah.
And everyone of these are exactly aligned. So we make a motion to prove nine ten and 11.
Thank you. I think we just do.
You guys have a question. Parker? Hi. Williams? Hi.
12 award contract agreement to clean uniform for RFQ-23-53
Motion to approve. Say it.
Perfect.
Williams.
Hi.
Doug Gold.
Be a step.
Hi.
17 in our local agreement between the city of Miami and Northeastern Oklahoma and the
image support of the local small business development center.
So may remember to the council.
This would be the third year of this contract, the contract in front of you, is for
$10,000 per year for two years.
This is a contract that we entered into a couple of years ago with the Oklahoma
Small Business Development Center in collaboration with any OANM, the Shawnee tribe, the
Peoria tribe, the wind up tribe, harvest, bank, and well-state bank.
And that collaboration between those three, we all combine our resources and share the cost
for the Oklahoma Small Business Development Center, which then our cost pays for half of having
the local Small Business Development Center, which the U.S. Small Business Administration provides
the second half of that funding.
So they pay for $2,000, and then us locally combine our resources to cover the match.
And for that, we get no cost entrepreneurial in Small Business Management advising to anyone
here in our community, really, in the county, that wants to take advantage of that Small Business
consultant, essentially.
They do a great job.
They're housed out there at any O, over the last couple of years.
They had helped and served over 2,281 clients here locally.
So these are people to have ideas that need help with the Small Business, that they're either struggling,
or they just don't know how to get it off the ground.
Maybe sometimes they have an idea, but they have no business plan, because they don't know how to
start.
And so they can seek out this SBC office, which is here at any O, and she will meet with it one
one, and help them develop a plan that they can take to go get funding if so needed or
raised funds to get the Small Business off the ground.
So again, this is a collaboration with three tribes and two of the banks in the state.
So with that, do you have to ask any questions?
Well, those 2,281, what the success rate is?
You know, Brian, I don't just so far as there's been, I'll tell you this, there's been 176
starts, but that was a number as of last year.
So I don't have the numbers for this year, how many starts, so maybe to be the number I get towards
the end of this fiscal year, but they've had 176.
capital infusion of $55,000 and provided $11,000 counseling hours and there's a quarterly
meeting that myself and the other partners attend on a quarterly basis which is housed
out at NEO and our local rep has to come in and present all of her numbers to the state
rep that she works for out of Oklahoma City and they have a pretty good oversight of her activity.
They ask really good questions and again we kind of go through what her plan is and who she's
met with and what her activities are and what we need to be doing to continue to increase
the numbers that she's helping. But all in all I think all the partners have been very pleased
you know wanting to continue the program and so that's why I brought this contract and you
will to see if the city in the council would be willing to continue on for another two years
with this program and these partners. You'll put that on and there is housing.
There is housing. There is housing in NEO. There is not fully in within NEO.
They're not fully in within NEO. They're more affiliated with the state state agency
which is the Oklahoma small business development center.
NEO just houses.
Just a single person or is there a local?
Okay. Make a motion.
In the if at any time we want a solder here and it comes present any of this to you all should be more than willing to do so.
It's bases and machines. They usually reach out to her.
I'll say it.
Okay.
14, 20, 20, 24 meetings schedule.
20, 20, 24 holidays schedule.
Motion no.
Thank.
Okay.
Thank you.
Question 2.
Second.
Williams?
Right.
Dental.
All right.
Hi.
17.
Another new business of any of which is the residents that's supposed to miss agenda.
18 staff reports.
19.
Mayor Council.
Community announcements.
Christmas.
Time is here.
And I don't know how many of you guys saw the video that I shared today from Colby Allen.
I'm really excited about this.
These, the Christmas balls that used to hang downtown Main Street.
They got damaged and lost forever.
Have been recreated.
And Colby and his team knocked us out of park.
They're awesome.
Bill Osborne team with the Monite and Osborne drugs have been paid for the project to be done.
Colby and his team.
I mean, he's got their super talented.
I mean, they've measured and drilled holes.
And to try to replicate these things as close as possible.
I mean, I was called in a day for a little bit.
And thanks to his team for their efforts.
But he wanted to make them, you know, like the old ones.
But then he got thinking that probably wouldn't smart.
Because we need these things the last 20 or 30 years.
So they looked like them.
But they're a new updated version.
They're fiberglass and new technology.
But I'm excited about getting those home.
There's Tyler.
So that would be Tyler's gig to get these things home.
And we know you can do it.
Right?
So that's exciting.
Keisha has a downtown event on set the November 17th, 18th.
That's why I asked about that day to all go.
Because it kind of kicks off our holiday season.
And the holiday market would be down there.
That's called Christmas on Main Street.
His look Keisha's got.
We're having a live reindeer here.
Smallers.
Sandalbee here.
But snow machine.
And they're going to allow some really cool.
And then December 1st.
We have the community tree lighting.
Which Tyler and his team always do a great job with that.
Does that have Kevin and their team to a great job decorating downtown?
So I'm really excited about that.
I know there's going to be a fundraiser kickoff.
To start raising some funds for Christmas decorations.
So that'll be kicked off here pretty quick.
And Debbie East.
I think we'll be running that fundraiser.
So we appreciate her doing that.
I think though Jennifer kind of worked where that can be done.
And so we appreciate that.
Gosh, what else?
Then the pride will be on the second so lots of stuff happen just about every weekend leading up to Christmas now
So we're gonna have to do the we're gonna have to do another love local push
I was talking about that watch about
Explain into people
You know when you just spend their dollars here our local shops and if they can't get it here we need them to buy it online
Because that link you just she's talking about this if they go to job when we don't get any of those tax dollars
So
So so I'm excited about the Christmas season and I think I think the
The new ball ball balls with bulbs that Colby has made or probably
Excites of people
Especially people at your upper ear that you're up seeing those on
And then let's give a shout out to Shannon do on and jacked our apple for the the great deer hunt
My dough bows out there longer than I was but I was out there this weekend and it's great to be here
I mean really is to show our disabled veterans that we appreciate them and they had a great time
We had dinner that night at the banquet with a couple and the ladies that next to me with all she fans
So she gave me crap all weekend. I earned it. I deserve it, but you shouldn't
But really good really good people and you know Mark Wayne Mollon came in and
Stopped by for a little bit, but
It was just a it was just a good time good event for those folks. I don't want guy tagged out like in
This first 30 minutes. He got a buck and his doubt and then you want to go fishing
There's a good shit in other years. I was very good fishing, but if you get the opportunity
They need volunteers for that
Dax getting up there in the years Shannon has a bad back. These guys work there tails off. I don't stop for weeks. Lead up to that
So if you have opportunity to
Volunteer for that. It's really good thing
I think that's all I have
So
We'll be number 20. So you may enter now. I'll pile on to that real quick
one of the amazing event that is and
Gentlemen, I can't thank you enough for your support your proclamations that the city council did and being able to go
Thursday night to the banquet and read those and then be able to set and meet with these folks
CVV had put together some really great
swag bags
Great stuff
They just stay feel so welcome when they come here
That was one of the things that the president of the PDAMA was telling me is my Emma Oklahoma knows how to roll out the red carpet for these guys
He said it is truly awe inspiring
and they do this other places, but I don't think they do it anywhere like we do here in my
Oklahoma. Jack does an amazing job. All this happens at his property, which he spends
months preparing for Shannon Duhan, works his tail off. I mean that guy, he's up, I'd say son
up to sundown, but it's way beyond that. He's up and out there, cooking breakfast. I don't know,
they breakfast at five every morning before the hunt, and then they don't serve him dinner
until the guys get back at eight o'clock from the hunt. And so I know he doesn't leave till
no telling, nine, ten o'clock at night, if then, and it's back out there doing it the next day.
But these folks, these veterans that take advantage of this are the most humble individuals.
They don't ask for this, they don't expect this, but they certainly deserve this.
And it's an opportunity for them to get out and do something
probably normal that most of us take advantage of. You don't realize that we have the
opportunity to go out in the woods and run around and do things like that. And it's just far
into these folks. But for them to go out there, be treated the way they are,
and have this opportunity, I know, means the world to them, because I've met with them and talked
to them multiple times. So anyway, anything that we can ever do this is we need to be stepping
up and helping them and helping Shannon. We don't want to wear Shannon out.
I did get out there this weekend and was able to help him and I can't hear her. I keep up with Shannon.
But I did the best I could and I'm just out there to do whatever and how this guy ever learned to cook
for hundreds of people's be on me. Of the many talents Shannon do on has that guy can cook for
100 people. Multiple meals of all different types, mostly cage it. But it was really good. He taught me a lot
of stuff. I mean he had me stuff and pork chops with boot and I only knew it boot and it was good.
In Christa 2, Christa 2 on here that works in the courts. It was been, she was out there all week and two,
just cooking her heart out. So I had to ask those folks, hats off to Jack and all that he does and thrilled
that we get to be a part of it in any way that we can. So thank you all for your support.
21 of the German motion. Second.